<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Littlediobolic</title>
        <link>http://littlediobolic.github.io/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Littlediobolic</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 12:12:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="http://littlediobolic.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Configure Apple Magic Trackpad 2 Gestures on Manjaro KDE</title>
            <link>http://littlediobolic.github.io/posts/magic-trackpad/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 12:12:00 -0400</pubDate>
            
            <guid>http://littlediobolic.github.io/posts/magic-trackpad/</guid>
            <description>Intro I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen any full-length tutorials for getting the Apple Magic Trackpad 2, or really any multi-touch track-pad, working in Manjaro, or more specifically KDE, yet so I figured I&amp;rsquo;d write down how I did it. Most of the info I got was from the libinput-gestures Github page if you would like to check it out. The device works out of the box with left, right, and middle-click as well as 2 finger scrolling.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="intro">Intro</h3>
<p>I haven&rsquo;t seen any full-length tutorials for getting the Apple Magic Trackpad 2, or really any multi-touch track-pad, working in Manjaro, or more specifically KDE, yet so I figured I&rsquo;d write down how I did it. Most of the info I got was from the libinput-gestures <a href="https://github.com/bulletmark/libinput-gestures">Github page</a> if you would like to check it out. The device works out of the box with left, right, and middle-click as well as 2 finger scrolling. But to get the rest of the features you need to set a few things up. YMMV on whether or not everything in this works for you.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="getting-started">Getting Started</h3>
<p>The very first thing you should know is that for fully supported drivers you need to be on at least Linux version <em>4.20</em>, I am running on <em>5.4.43-1</em> which is Manjaro&rsquo;s LTS kernel release.</p>
<p>Once you are on a kernel version that supports the Trackpad drivers, plug in the device and it should immediately start working for the most part. However, the multi-finger gestures do not work, as nothing is currently bound to them. For that, we need <em>libinput-gestures</em>. I&rsquo;ve seen a couple forum posts to suggest using other input libraries but the only one that works in this scenario I&rsquo;ve seen is libinput.</p>
<p><code>sudo pacman -S libinput-gestures</code></p>
<p>Go ahead and install <em>libinput-gestures</em>. The first thing we should do is add our user to the <em>input</em> group.</p>
<p><code>sudo gpasswd -a $USER input</code></p>
<p>Form there we can run the following commands:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">libinput-gestures-setup autostart  
libinput-gestures-setup start  
</code></pre></div><p>Alright awesome, now that its up and running we can go ahead and shut it back down and start building our config.</p>
<p><code>libinput-gestures-setup stop</code></p>
<p>Your config file exists in 2 places: <code>/etc/libinput-gestures.conf</code> and <code>~/.config/libinput-gestures.conf</code>. The former is for default gestures, all users on the system will share these gestures. The one in <em>.config</em> is personal to your user. I will be using the one in <em>.config</em> but it shouldn&rsquo;t matter.</p>
<p><code>nano ~/.config/libinput-gestures.conf</code></p>
<p>Here is a paste of my config file:</p>
<pre><code># Swipe threshold (0-100)  
swipe_threshold 0  
  
# Gestures  
gesture swipe up 3 konsole  
gesture swipe down 3 xdotool key Super_L+Page_Down  
gesture pinch out 3 xdotool key Ctrl+F9  
gesture swipe right 3 xdotool key Ctrl+Shift+F2  
gesture swipe left 3 xdotool key Ctrl+Shift+F1  
</code></pre><p>The format for the gestures is pretty straight forward: <code>gesture</code> means just that, create a gesture. Then you define the gesture type. These can be <code>swipe</code> and <code>pinch</code>. Then specify the direction with <code>up</code> <code>down  </code> <code>left</code> and <code>right</code>. Next you define the number of fingers to perform the gesture with. I have not testedwith any more than 3 fingers for gestures, I would imagine 4 works though I dont know about 5 and above.<br>
Finally you give it the command to run. For this I would suggest <em>xdotool</em> as you can pretty much do anything that the mouse and keyboard can do with that command. Mine just do keybinds though you can do some mo<br>
re complex macro&rsquo;ing if youre into that sort of thing.</p>
<p>Once you save your config file run:</p>
<p><code>libinput-gestures-setup start</code></p>
<p>Doing the defined gestures should run the command you specified. Should you notice that its not a quick way to ensure that libinput is running the command is to stop <em>libinput-gestures</em> again and then run:</p>
<pre><code>libinput-gestures -d  
(Ctrl+C to stop)  
</code></pre><p>This will show you the commands that would be ran once a recognizable gesture is detected. If all is good go ahead and start <em>libinput-gestures</em> again.</p>
<h3 id="is-that-it">Is that it&hellip;?</h3>
<p>Well yes, but actually no&hellip; At this point the track-pad will work and you can bind gestures to your hearts content. However, you&rsquo;ll soon notice that if you connect the track-pad through Bluetooth, and have to reconnect the track-pad, that gestures stop registering. The gestures will also stop working sometimes once waking from a lock or sleep.</p>
<p>The only way to fix this is by restarting the gesture service. You can do this by hand, but using <em>dbus-action</em> is a more elegant solution. Here is how to set that up.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="configuring-d-bus-action">Configuring D-Bus Action</h3>
<p>First things first is to install <em>dbus-action</em>. This is something that needs to be installed from the AUR, so do that however you would install any other AUR package. For me I use pamac:</p>
<p><code>sudo pamac build dbus-action</code></p>
<p>Once built we can start configuring the service. At this point we need to use the following command to find the message that is displayed on the D-Bus whenever we connect our track-pad. Run:</p>
<p><code>dbus-action -m all</code></p>
<p>From there you an try connecting and disconnecting your track-pad a couple times to see if you are able to find the message. For me it was <code>workingTouchpadFoundChanged</code> on my desktop but my laptop actually showed <code>mousePluggedInChanged</code> so you will need to see which one appears for you:</p>
<p><code>session org.kde.touchpad workingTouchpadFoundChanged: 1</code></p>
<p>Now that we have that, we need to create the config file that will tell <em>dbus-action</em> to restart the gesture service once it detects a touchpad being plugged in. Create a file <code>~/.config/dus-action.conf</code> and paste the following:</p>
<pre><code>triggers:   
 - bus: session  
  interface: org.kde.touchpad  
  member: workingTouchpadFoundChanged  
  values:  
   1: &quot;libinput-gestures-setup restart&quot;
</code></pre><p>Save that and then we need to run the same steps for this as we did for <em>libinput-gestures-setup</em>:</p>
<pre><code>dbus-action-setup start
dbus-action-setup autostart
</code></pre><p>Once that is running it will begin restarting the service once it detects a track-pad has been plugged in. You can obviously test by re-plugging in your track-pad and ensure the gesture service restarts as expected. This should restart the gesture service when both plugged in via the lightning cable or when connected via Bluetooth.</p>
<p>At this point your track-pad should be completely good to go! You can bind the track-pad to issue whatever commands you are looking for. I have had really good luck with the responsiveness of the gestures and scrolling on the touch-pad. This allowed me to bind several workflow shortcuts I normally use to the track-pad instead of relying on the shortcut only.</p>
<p>If you feel like I missed anything or the setup didnt work for you, you can get in contact with me via my <a href="https://keybase.io/littlediobolic">Keybase</a> or any of my attached accounts.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
